太空堡垒卡拉狄加 【 前情提要 】
ADAMA: Previously on Battlestar Galactica.
祝贺你晋升为上尉  抱歉 我没到场
Congratulations on making Captain. Sorry I wasn't there.
谢谢  长官
Thank you, sir.
你的母亲近来好吗?
How's your mother?
快结婚了
Getting married.
北面的群山之中 有一条小溪
In the mountains north of here there's this little stream.
溪水清澈见底 宛如明镜
The water is so clear, it's like looking through glass.
我想在那里造一座小屋
I'm thinking of building a cabin.
你和凯莉闹矛盾了?
APOLLO: You and Cally have a fight?
你没听到我们吵架?  我们以为都可以卖票参观了
You didn't hear us? I figured we should have sold tickets.
敬婚姻 这也是我们开酒吧的原因
To marriage, why we build bars.
让波塔尔就此消失 还为时不晚
It's not too late for Baltar to just disappear.
我们不能那么做
I can't do that.
尽管他恶贯满盈 可他始终是我们中的一员
For all his crimes, he's one of us.
那下一步怎么办?
So what happens next?
让他得到公正的审判
We give him his trial.
泰上校要见您  上将      让他进来吧
MAN: Colonel Tigh to see you, Admiral. Enter.
起来得挺早啊
You're up early.
睡不着  还不如起来做点事
Couldn't sleep, so I thought I'd make myself useful.
结婚周年快乐  比尔
Happy anniversary, Bill.
乖
CALLY: Hey...
没事的
Shh... It's okay.
It's okay.
我说不准 你再帮我试一下
I don't know. Here. Just double check it for me.
你老爸越来越熟练了
I think Daddy's getting good at this.
老爸的手腕不想再被烫了
Daddy's tired of burning his wrists.
我得准备好 咱们要值早班
We've got to get ready. We've got morning watch.
我们今天不是要陪尼奇么
I thought we were spending the day with Nicky.
对  我也是这么想的 可拉斯肯和佩里请了病假
Yeah. So did I, until Laskin and Perry called in sick.
乖哦
It's okay.
那你就主动提出顶替他们?
So, you volunteered us in their place?
我们几乎都没有时间休息了
We barely get any time off as it is.
凯莉  你也知道甲板上缺人手
Cal, you know the deck is short-handed.
自从我们到了这里  甲板上就一直缺人手
The deck has been short-handed since we got here.
尼奇和日托人员相处的时间 比和我们在一起的时间还多
All I know is frakking daycare workers see more of Nicky than we do.
在日托人员学会拆飞机之前
Yeah, well, until the daycare workers figure out how to strip a Viper,
只能这样
this is the way it's gonna be.
来吧  小子
Hey, buddy. Come here.
我知道  我知道  你刚躺下  是吧?
I know, I know, I know. You just laid down, too, didn't you?
来吧
Come here. I got you.
我带他去日托那里
Here you go. I'll take him to daycare.
你干嘛
What are you doing?
忘记拿东西了吧?
Hey! Forgetting something?
有什么日程安排?
What's on duty schedule?
没什么趣事 医务室附近装了一个 二氧化碳洗涤器
Nothing sexy. CO2 scrubber's out near sick bay.
厨房里有条水管坏了
Broken water line in the galley.
哦…
Oh...
多数蝮蛇战机进了干船坞
Now that most of our Vipers are out of dry-dock,
轮机长要去看一下12号过渡舱的自动控制装置
Chief's gonna have a look at the servos in airlock 12.
签一下吧
Could you, please...
就这么多?
Is that it?
舰队里风平浪静
Fleet's quiet.
你去休息一下吧  我来值第一班
You can use some time for yourself. I can handle first watch.
我还是按计划工作
I'll be keeping my schedule.
这只是普通的一天而已
This is just another day.
普通的一天?
CAROLANNE: Just another day?
或许我本应该嫁给他 而不是你
Maybe I should have married him instead of you.
这事谁都知道了
ADAMA: I could have sold tickets to that.
我们有过幸福时光
We had some good times.
可发生矛盾的时候更多
But more bad.
你却依旧会想起我
CAROLANNE: But you keep bringing me back, anyway.
只有在这天才会想起我
Just this one day.
年复一年 只是我不明白
Year after year. Only thing I can't understand is
为什么呢
why?
我也不明白
Neither do I.
打扰了  长官
JAFFEE: Excuse me, sir.
放在桌子上吧  大兵
Put it on the table, Private.
我叫扎菲  长官
Jaffee, sir.
还有什么事么  上将?
Would there be anything else, Admiral?
没事了  扎菲
That will be all, Jaffee.
这将是漫长的一天   一向如此
CAROLANNE: It's going to be a long day. ADAMA: It always is.
早安  轮机长
Morning, Chief.
尼奇还好吧?      恩  他没事
Is Nicky okay? Yeah, he's fine.
我把他放到日托那里后 他第一次没哭
First time he didn't cry when I dropped him off at daycare.
菲戈斯基 今天至少要假装干些活吧?
So, Figurski, you gonna at least pretend to do something today?
该死的洗涤器
Frakking scrubber.
阿达玛动动手腕签一个工作单
Takes Adama two seconds to sign off on an order
我们就要忙上一整天
that's gonna take us all day to finish.
反正是你要忙上一整天
Oh, it will take you all day, anyhow.
希里克丝  凯丽 跟我去12号过渡舱
Seelix. Cally. You're with me. Airlock 12.
希里克丝 去把门打开  好吗?      好
Seelix, can you get the door? Yep.
这地方真是他妈的一团糟
This place is a frakking mess.
赛昂人把这里炸得面目全非
Yeah. The Cylons blew the hell out of it.
自从检修组把弹洞修补好之后 就没人来过这里
Nobody's been down here since damage-control plugged the holes.
希里克丝 在里面能听到我说话吗?      能
Seelix, can you hear me there? Yeah.
去找一下过渡舱的电路图吧
You want to see if you can find the electrical diagram for the airlock?
好 我倒是找到了别人的陈年午餐
Okay. Ooh, I did find somebody's year-old lunch.
他连哭都没哭吗?
He didn't even cry?
阿莉  我说过了 尼奇没事
Cal, I told you, Nicky is fine.
谁都可以带上工具包来这里
Yeah, and anybody could have dragged a tool bag down here.
不一定非要我来
It didn't have to be me.
总要有人来
Yeah, well, it had to be somebody.
你比别人都更熟悉这些齿轮装置
You know these gearing systems better than anybody.
你想让我怎么做?  就因为你是我老婆 我就要特殊对待你?
What do you want me to do? Give you special treatment because you're my wife?
那成何体统?      我不管
How would that look? I don't care!
我们还在装作我们的生活从未改变
We keep trying to pretend like nothing's changed,
和在新卡布里卡之前一样吗?
that our lives are exactly like they were before we went to New Caprica.
可是确实已经不同了
But it is different.
我们已经结婚生子了
We're married. We have a son.
只是一时的困境罢了
Yeah, it's just a little rough patch.
如果是一世呢?
What if rough patches are all we have left?
我们发过誓会亲自抚养尼奇 记得吗?
We swore we were gonna raise Nicky ourselves, remember?
恩  我们发过很多誓
Yeah, well. We swore a lot of things.
可赛昂人也没有合作精神  不是吗?
The Cylons didn't exactly cooperate, did they?
把线缆切割器给我好吗?
You want to give me those wire cutters?
搞什么鬼?
What the hell?
他奶奶的
For frak's sake.
希里克丝  你在做什么?  把门打开
Seelix? What are you doing? Open the door.
我什么也没做呀
I didn't do anything.
轮机长 我检测到里面出现了压力差
SEELIX: Chief, I'm picking up a pressure differential in there.
虽然并不强烈
It's nothing drastic.
但你们的氧气确实在流失
But you guys are definitely losing air.
没什么稀奇的
Oh, it doesn't take much.
空气流量传感器一旦探测到 一定大小的裂缝
Once the airflow sensors detect a big enough leak,
内门便会自动关闭
all the inner doors are designed to drop automatically.
这只是一种安全措施
It's just a safety precaution.
我觉得好安全啊
I feel safer already.
等一下 你是说船体有裂口?
Wait a second. Are you saying that the hull's been breached?
说"裂口"有些夸张了  不过氧气还是去了其他地方
Well, "breach" is a bit dramatic, but the air's going somewhere.
一定是我们进来的时候  有个补丁裂开了
One of these patches must have cracked when we came in.
只要我们塞住裂口  恢复了压力  门就会打开
Soon as we plug it and restore the pressure, the door should open.
然后我们就可以从工作单中找出是哪个死鬼焊接的
Then we can pull the work orders on whoever made these frakking welds
然后扁他一顿
and kick their asses.
最重要的是要活下去
Yeah, well, the most important thing is to keep breathing,
所以先要找到裂缝
so let's just find the leak.
啊…
Ah...
在这里 就是这里了
This is it, right here. This one.
李森负责值第一班
Leeson takes first watch.
金赛负责核对值勤表  金赛负责核对值勤表
Kinsey checks the roster. Kinsey checks the roster.
扎菲负责给我送咖啡
Jaffee brings me coffee.
你还在这么做吗?  锻炼记忆力?
Are you still doing that? The memory exercises?
你真以为他们希望你能把他们的名字都记住?
Do you really think they expect you to know all of their names?
你还是一点没变
You never change, do you?
我想这是早死的乐趣之一
One of the joys of being long dead, I suppose.
快点吧  你与劳拉的约会要迟到了
Now, hurry. You're going to be late meeting Laura.
也许她就是喜欢坏孩子  可她不是第一个人
CAROLANNE: Maybe she's got a thing for bad boys. She wouldn't be the first.
她是十二殖民地的总统
She's the President of the Twelve Colonies.
对不起  对不起      这是当然
Oh. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. Of course.
反正你已经建立了你那有如神灵的一面
Since you've created one God-like facade for yourself,
为什么不给她创造一个呢?
why not invent another one for her?
可以作为你和她保持距离的另一个借口
It's another excuse to keep your distance.
上将
Admiral.
总统阁下
Madam President.
近来可好?      很好
How are you? Very good.
不好意思 我知道这些问题都可以通过无线电来解决
I'm sorry. I'm sure this all could have been done over the wireless,
不过说实话 我在殖民者一号上呆得有些心烦气躁
but very frankly, I was going a little stir crazy on Colonial One
必须出来走走
and I had to get out.
深空驾驶员把这称为"焦头烂额"
Deep space pilots used to call it OBE.
什么是"焦头烂额"?    事情太多 忙得焦头烂额
What's "OBE"? "Overcome by events. "
随时欢迎你来这里 这你是知道的
And you're always welcome here. You know that.
你看完这个可能就不会那么想了
Well, you may not feel that way after you finish this.
托莉拟订了一份日程草案
Tory actually drew up an agenda.
又是波塔尔
Baltar again.
嗯
Mmm.
我们就不能把他还给赛昂人么?
Can't we just give him back to the Cylons?
我也想那么做 可惜的是…
You know how much I love that idea. Unfortunately,
考虑到我从卡布里卡六号那里收集到的情报
given what little I was able to glean from the Caprica Six,
我认为赛昂人并不愿意接受他 所以我们左右为难
I don't think the Cylons would take him back, so we're stuck.
好吧 审判这个混蛋  让他快点消失
Fine. Then try the son of a bitch and be done with it.
我们要审判他 但要依照什么法律?
We have to give him a trial, but under what law?
卡布里卡?  派亢? 特诺朗?
Caprican? Picon? Tauron?
是否要有陪审团在场?  是否安排一个独立仲裁庭?
Do we give him a jury trial? Do we set up a tribunal?
我们甚至还没有 一座完整的法律文库
We don't even have anything closely resembling a comprehensive law library.
而这个舰队 还缺乏法律人才
And this fleet is not exactly brimming with legal talent.
如果你让律师介入 他们会把这次审判拖上几个月
You bring lawyers into this, they're gonna drag you around for months.
令尊不曾是卡布里卡的一名律师吗?
Wasn't your father an attorney on Caprica?
对 我也告诉过你 我与他相处得不太好
Yes. And I told you that I didn't get along with him very well.
好吧
Oh, right. Okay.
我准备建立一个组织委员会 不过坦率地说
I'm ready to set up an organizing committee, but frankly,
要让满屋的法律学者按章办事是强人所难
trying to get a room full of legal scholars to stay on task is like herding cats,
所以我要选拔一位委员会主席
and so I need to set up a chairman of this committee,
一个可以做出艰难决策的人
somebody who can make a hard decision
不会被法律术语控制或束缚的人
and who won't get seduced and bogged down by all the legalese.
有合适人选了吗?      我倒是早有人选了
Do you have a candidate? As a matter of fact, I do.
我认为李可以
I was thinking Lee.
可能"有其爷爷  必有其孙子" 你认为呢?
Like grandfather, like grandson, perhaps. What do you think?
不是我说他无法胜任
I'm not gonna say he's incapable of handling it,
只是他从没显露过对法律有兴趣
but he's never shown any type of interest in law.
我知道  但事情是这样
I know, but here's the thing.
我们可以利用律师来剖析法律
We can use the lawyers to parse the law,
但我们真正需要的是能够明辩是非曲直的人
but we really need people who actually know the difference
李就是这种人
between right and wrong. That's Lee.
我会和他谈谈   好
I'll talk to him. Good.
还有一件事  上将
Also, Admiral?
今天我可以在你的船上度过吗?
I was wondering if you mind if I stayed on your ship for the rest of the day.
当然可以
Please. By all means.
我不太好意思说 就是…
This is very difficult for me to say, but
我要去健身房
I'm going to go to the gym.
你可要小心了
Prepare yourself.
人多的时候 里面有股臭鞋的味道
On its best days, it smells like the inside of a shoe.
看看还有没要修补的
See if there's another patch in there.
这里要双重加固
I want to double up on this one and make sure it holds.
快  阿莉 早完事
Come on, Cal. Faster is better. The sooner we do this,
早出去    我早听到了
the sooner we can get out of here. I heard you the first time.
你越来越善于 无视这些周遭的事情了
CAROLANNE: You're getting better at ignoring all of that.
官兵们突然肃静  用眼角余光瞥你
That sudden hush, those sidelong glances.
这些都曾让你很不安
That really used to get to you.
倒是想不起来这些能让你畏惧过
Don't ever recall being able to intimidate you.
对
That's right.
但早在你成为上将之前  我就已经认识你了
But I knew you long before you were the Admiral.
当你还只是比尔的时候
Back when you were just Bill.
抛妻弃子的那个人
My husband who wasn't there. The father who left.
只是比尔的时候
Just Bill.
谁是比尔・阿达玛?  这还是一个好问题
Who is Bill Adama, anyway? Still a good question.
我都不知道是否能得到答案
I wonder if I'll get an answer.
49天没有出现了
Forty-nine days without a sighting.
看来真把"烤面包机"们吓跑了
Maybe we finally scared the toasters off.
对  纳卓  就你那烂技术把他们吓得心里有阴影了
Oh, yeah, Narcho. Your crap flying has put the fear of the Gods in them.
你好吗  兄弟?
What's up, buddy?
怎么了?
What's the matter with you?
不好意思 我这里长了一片奇怪的红疹
Sorry. I've got the weirdest rash.
真的?
Really?
但愿她值得你这样  兄弟
Hope she was worth it, buddy.
起立!
Ten-hut.
稍息
At ease.
在我们开始之前 我想做个调查
Before we get started, I want a show of hands.
你们这群傻蛋中有几个人会数数?
How many of you boneheads know how to count?
因为机库中的数数声不绝于耳
Because I keep hearing numbers being thrown around the hangar deck.
47  然后是48...
Forty-seven, then 48,
自从我们最后一次发现敌人到现在  已有49天了
now 49 days since our last enemy contact.
我看得出再难一点的数学 你们中大部分人可能也不会
Now, I realize that any higher math is probably beyond most of you.
所以我就简单地说
So, I'm going to make this real simple for you.
1是你们唯一需要记住的数字
One is the only number you need to remember.
因为只要一名驾驶员疏忽大意
Because all it takes is for one pilot to let his guard down,
一名电子干扰员错过雷达上所出现的目标
one ECO to miss a dradis contact,
而赛昂人就会突然出现在我们眼前了
and suddenly, the Cylons are on top of us.
这时候就会死人
That's when people die.
他像我们两个人一样
ADAMA: He's like both of us.
高傲  顽固  愤怒
Proud, stubborn and angry.
可他已经可以独自决断了 尤其是近几个月以来
But he's coming into his own, especially in the last few months.
这事不要告诉我
CAROLANNE: Don't tell me.
要告诉他   他知道
Tell him. He knows.
知道什么?
He knows what?
知道上将会说他有杰出表现?
That the Admiral's going to give him a good performance review?
或是他的父亲爱他?
Or that his father loves him?
别告诉我上将对李也要展现那一面
Don't tell me the Admiral's facade extends to Lee, too.
编队飞行
APOLLO: Formation flying,
偏角射击 战术
deflection shooting, tactics,
连续飞行 直到你们每个人三项都合格
doing touch-and-goes, until every last one of you hits an OK3.
红队和蓝队先来 黄队和绿队随后开始
Red and blue sections will go first. Yellow and green will follow.
10分钟内升空  解散
Skids up in 10 minutes. Dismissed!
星芭 如果你有异议 我也不想听
Starbuck, if you've got a problem, I don't want to hear about it.
嗯
Mmm!
一周前你可没对我们如此严厉呀
My only problem is that you didn't preach that sermon a week ago.
你最好换些花样
You might want to find some new material, though.
自从我们来了这里 老头子一直在用"一个致命错误"这句话
The old man's been using that "one fatal mistake" line since we got here.
你要偷学别人的话 就要找最出色的人偷学
Well, if you're gonna steal, steal from the best.
长官
Sir.
今天对他们挺严格的
Pretty tough on them today.
忠言逆耳
Well, a kick in the butt is worth a thousand words.
您对我的管教就够严的
Gods know you kicked mine enough.
一切都好吧?
Everything okay?
恩  和以前的几个早上一样
Yeah, it's been one of those mornings.
总统想快些审判波塔尔
The President wants to take the fast track on Baltar's trial.
她想找一位可以主管准备工作的人
She's looking for someone to take charge of the preliminaries,
来把法律体制搭配起来
help cobble together the legal framework.
她想让我选派你
She wants me to assign you.
说笑吧?
You're kidding.
有兴趣?
Interested?
更多的是意外
More surprised.
她说了为什么选派我吗?
Did she say why she asked for me?
她需要值得信赖的人选
Well, she's gonna need someone that she can trust.
你绝对符合这个标准
You definitely fit that.
我还记得你稍年轻的时候 去你祖父家
I remember when you were younger, you'd go visit your grandfather's house.
你对他的那些论文和法律书籍很痴迷
You were fascinated with his papers and his law books.
我也想过 当时自己鬼鬼崇崇的样子
And there was me, thinking I was being sly,
独自一人潜入他的办公室
sneaking off into his office all by myself.
现在只是白日做梦了 但我在参军之前…
You know, I guess it's a pipe dream now, but for five minutes there,
真的考虑过当律师
I really did consider "lawyer"
会是我未来的职业之一
as one of the dozen careers that I could go into before I joined the service.
嗯
Hmm.
这我倒不知道
I never knew that.
应该是在"生爸爸气"那段时间
Well, it was probably during one of my "angry at Dad" phases.
总之 这是不可能的
Anyway, it's impossible.
即使我想帮忙  也帮不上
Even if I wanted to help out, there's no way.
就算一周比较轻松  空军队长也要全天忙
CAG's duty's already 24/7, even on a light week.
恩 我猜也是
Yeah. I assumed that.
少校 我们准备好了
NARCHO: Major? We're ready for you.
失陪了
Excuse me.
反正都要试一下
Yeah, well, one's gonna have to do.
希里克斯 检查一下压力 如果补丁能支撑住
Seelix? Check the pressure. If that patch holds,
几分钟内压力就可以平衡 门就会打开了
we're gonna equalize in a few minutes. This door's gonna open.
好
Okay.
见鬼
Oh, my Gods.
他们怎么样了?      还活着
How are they doing? Still alive.
三级警报 14号甲板上出现船体裂口
WOMAN ON P.A.: This is a Condition 3 alert. Full breach on Deck 14.
轮机长
Chief.
上将...
Admiral?
看来我已经造成了  无法挽回的损失
I seem to have turned this into a full-blown fubar.
如果您能把这道门打开  可真是帮了我们大忙
You'd be doing us a hell of a favor to get those doors open.
我们得把他们救出来
We gotta get them out of there.
运动运动  运动运动
Keep moving. Keep moving.
过渡舱被设计为在舱压突然降低时就会关闭舱门
The airlock is designed to lock down if the pressure decreases unexpectedly.
所以只要... 我了解这套系统
So, as soon as that patch... I know the system.
我们还有其他办法  还有备用方案
We have redundancies, we have backups...
手控超驰装置已经失灵
The manual override is down.
无法打开内门
There is no way of getting those inner doors to open.
过渡舱一定是在逃出新卡布里卡的时候遭到了重击
The thing must have taken heavy damage on the way out of New Caprica.
整艘船都受到了重创
Whole ship's taken a pounding.
我们得在干船坞中呆上六周  来修补弹坑
We need six weeks in dry-dock just to hammer out the dings,
更别说还要处理结构损伤
let alone tackle the structural damage.
他们还有多少时间?
How much time do they have?
以裂缝的尺寸来看 不到半小时 可能就会没有氧气
From a leak that size, they'll be out of air in half an hour, maybe less.
那些是密闭门 至少要用一小时才能切开
Those are blast doors. It would take at least an hour to cut through them.
为什么不在观察室里安置炸药?
TIGH: Why don't we put explosives in the observation booth?
把玻璃炸碎  拉他们出来
Blow the glass, pull them out...
行不通 那面玻璃足以承受泰里恩爆炸
No, that glass is strong enough to withstand a tylium explosion.
能把玻璃炸碎的话
Anything strong enough to take out the glass
蒂罗尔和凯莉也活不了
will take out Tyrol and Cally at the same time.
我要的是一个营救计划
I need a rescue plan,
不是诸多借口
not excuses.
七秒钟
Seven seconds.
因为这是在外太空作业 我们还需要10秒的增压时间
And another 10 to re-pressurize, since we'll be doing this in open space.
难上加难
That's pushing it.
我提这个问题可能很傻
All right, this might be a stupid question,
但有人尝试过这样的营救方法吗?
but has anyone ever tried a rescue like this before?
还没有人这么疯狂过
No one has ever been crazy enough.
管不了那么多了 我们没时间了  准备起飞
Doesn't matter. We're out of time. Prep for launch.
只剩18分钟了
We've only got 18 minutes left.
好  走吧 开始行动
All right, let's go. We're on.
加伦
CALLY: Galen.
过渡舱门还是卡在那里  轮机长
ADAMA: Airlock's still jammed, Chief.
超驰控制也没有反应
Overrides are not responding.
看来我们无计可施了
Guess we're kind of running out of options.
我会派人从前门救你们出去
I'm gonna take you out through the front door.
你要派一艘船在外面...
You're going to put a ship out there,
搭建一个浮坞环?
rig up some kind of docking collar?
几分钟之内 你们的氧气就会耗尽  没有时间搭环
You'll be out of air in a few minutes. There's no time for a collar.
长官 可我们没有增压服来进行太空行走
Sir, if you're talking about an EVA, we don't have pressure suits.
我们别无选择
We don't have a choice.
雅典娜会把猛禽机悬停在过渡舱外
Athena's going to position her Raptor in front of the airlock,
然后敞开舱门
hatch open.
我们会把那道门的螺栓炸掉
I'm gonna blow the bolts right off of that door.
当门被炸开后 你们就得跳向飞船
And when it opens up, you're gonna have to jump for it.
现在你们两个听好
Now, listen to me, both of you.
你们能行的
You can do this.
人在没有增压服的情况下  可以在外太空存活一分钟
People have been able to live up to a minute in exposure without a suit.
上将  这可说不准
Admiral, I don't know.
我们一会再聊 准备好
We'll talk later. Get ready.
雅典娜  我是卡拉狄加 你有优先通行权
WOMAN: Athena, Galactica, you have priority clearance.
其他船只已被转移
All other traffic is being waved away.
等一下
CALLY: Wait.
那尼奇呢?
What about Nicky?
上将说得对 我们要准备一下
Admiral's right. We have to prep.
得把所有东西 从这里移到门口去
I'll move everything away from here to the door.
加伦?
Galen?
我们都知道舰队里那些
We both know what happens to kids in the fleet
没有父母照顾的孩子会怎么样
when their parents aren't there for them.
阿波罗和小杜 他们会照看他的
Apollo and Dee. They'll take care of him.
不行 不能是驾驶员
No. No pilots.
不能让他再经历这样的事了
He's not going through this twice.
长官?
Sir?
有一个平民百姓家
There's a civilian family.
母亲叫苏珊・戴克勒 她有一个小女儿
Mother's name is Susan Stettler. She has a little girl.
如果我们有什么不测…   这件事交给我吧
If anything happens to us... I'll see to it.
那时候是我自私 我只是想和你…
I was being selfish. I wanted you with me.
像从前一样
Like old times.
我没有考虑到尼奇
I didn't think about Nick.
对不起
I'm sorry.
上将会把我们救出去的
Admiral's gonna get us out of here, okay?
我们来照顾尼奇
We're gonna take care of Nicky.
在外面多呆几秒钟 就会出现严重暴露损伤
More than a few seconds out there, and we're talking severe exposure.
减压病 最起码也是失温
Decompression sickness. At the very least, hypothermia.
他们可能会被冻死
They could freeze to death.
确保让科特尔准备好高压氧仓室
Make sure Cottle's got his hyperbaric chamber ready.
对不起
CALLY: I'm sorry.
卡拉狄加  我是阿波罗 猛禽机横悬在12号过渡舱外
Galactica, Apollo. Bringing Raptor into position at B1-12.
把面罩戴上
TYROL: Put your mask on.
好了  听好  我们没时间等过渡舱门被炸开…
All right, listen up. We don't have time to hang back
以后再折回
until the airlock doors blow.
所以可能会经受一些残余氧的气流冲击
So we're liable to experience some turbulence from the residual oxygen,
甚至是碎片的撞击
maybe even some shrapnel hits.
雅典娜 你要准备好调整方向
Athena, you're going to have to be ready to compensate.
交给我吧  少校
I'm on it, Major.
我们会保持原位 直到轮机长和凯莉安全上机
I'll hold position until Chief and Cally are secured.
把这件事做好吧
Let's just get this done.
卡拉狄加  我是阿波罗 猛禽机舱门已打开
Galactica, Apollo. Raptor door is open.
我们在原地待命 已准备好执行任务
We're standing by. Ready to execute.
轮机长  凯莉
Chief, Cally,
猛禽机已经就位 我们要开始了
Raptor's in position. We've got to go now.
准备好炸开舱门  按我口令
Get ready to blow the hatch on my mark.
好了 无论发生什么情况你都要抱紧我
Okay. No matter what, you hold on to me.
不要放手  准备好了?
And don't let go. Okay.
三
Three...
二
Two...
一  炸开它
One. Do it.
小心! 向右侧滚 向右侧滚
APOLLO: Watch out! Bank right! Bank right!
我就位了
ATHENA: We're in position!
机首上仰 上仰!
Pull up your nose! Pull up!
好了 别动了
Got it! Hold it right there!
卡拉狄加  我是阿波罗  猛禽机接到目标 增压完毕
Galactica, Apollo. Raptor is secured and pressurized.
他们的情况不妙
They are in rough shape.
我们要把他们立即送去医务室
We've got to get them to sick bay right away.
进来吧
Come in.
轮机长和凯莉的情况怎么样?
So, any word on Chief and Cally?
都活了下来 不过科特尔医生还在评估他们的状况
They're alive, but Doc Cottle is still evaluating their condition.
您这是怎么了?
So, are you going to tell me what's going on with you?
是这个日子
It's this day.
我的天 是您的结婚周年纪念日
My Gods, your wedding anniversary.
我把这事给忘到脑后了
I had totally forgotten.
这么做看起来可能很傻 特别是因为它已经结束了 但…
Probably seems foolish, especially the way it all ended up, but...
还是...
Still...
它对我还是很重要
It still means something to me.
我们还从没谈论过这件事
We've never talked about it.
那次离婚
The divorce.
你母亲
Your mother.
那时候对大家来说都不好受
It was a bad time for all of us.
你母亲给你和你哥一个家 安居之所
Your mother gave you and your brother a home, stability.
爸 我知道 您宁愿相信这些都是真事 可是..
Dad, I know you want to believe that, but...
算了 都是很久以前的事了
You know what? Forget it. It was a long time ago.
孩子 有话想说  就说出来
You have something to say, Son, just say it.
爸  我们确实没有露宿街头
Dad, we had four walls.
可安居之所?
But stability?
您也知道老妈情绪不定
My Gods, you know what Mom was like. I mean, the mood swings...
这也是您离开她的原因
It's why you left her.
我们之间确实有矛盾
We had problems, but...
但她还是很关心你和你哥的   自从你走后事情就发生了变化
She cared deeply for you and your brother. Things changed after you left.
有几次 她情绪失控
And, I mean, there were times when she lost control.
别信他说的话  比尔
CAROLANNE: Don't listen to him, Bill.
过后 她就会道歉
APOLLO: She would try and apologize.
向我们保证 她会改过自新
She would promise that she would make things better.
可随后就开始喝酒
But then she would just start drinking.
这样她的一切 花言巧语就…
And then all of her good intentions would just go flying
都付诸东流
out the frakking window.
这些是真的吗?
ADAMA: Is it true?
没想到你还会这样问我
I can't believe you'd even ask me that!
见鬼 这些是真的吗?
Damn it. Is it true?
直到有一天 连道歉都没有了
APOLLO: And then, one day, finally, the apologies even stopped.
够了
That's enough.
是你抛弃了我
CAROLANNE: You walked out on me!
是你抛弃了我!
You walked out on me!
堂堂的指挥官 可以带军作战!
The brilliant commander, who could lead all of his men into combat,
可就是不知道该怎么与自己的家人相处!
but he couldn't find a way to live with his own family!
我们从没在一个地方居住超过六个月
We never lived anywhere for more than six months!
就只是跟着你从一个基地到另一个基地
Just following you around from one base to another!
等着你回家
Waiting for you to come home!
可你要的不是我们
But you weren't here for any of us!
都是为了"伟大的阿达玛"自己!
It was always whatever was easiest for the great Adama!
他们需要的是你 他们是我们俩的孩子
They needed you. They were our children.
他们需要一个父亲
They needed a father.
在你这一生光辉的历程之中...
All through your glorious career,
让你引以为荣的就是 当上了一位将领
you have prided yourself on being a leader of men,
可以评判他人的是非功过
judging people,
总要做出艰难的抉择
always making the hard call.
可当遇到了你这一生中最重大的决定的时候
But when it came to the biggest decision of your life,
比尔  你却搞砸了
oh, Bill, you blew it.
我们从开始在一起就是个错误  可你却不肯承认
We were wrong for each other from day one, but you just couldn't accept that.
就是这样 这就是你总是想起我的原因
That's it. That's why you keep calling me back.
因为如果你承认犯了那个错误
Because if you had made that mistake,
你就会重新审视在此之前 你所有的决定
it would just call into question all of your other decisions.
她依旧是你的母亲  李
ADAMA: She was still your mother, Lee.
我爱她
I loved her.
我相信
APOLLO: I believe you.
我只是认为  她从没爱过你
I just don't think she ever loved you.
他在这边
He's right over here.
嗨
Hey.
我去了日托那里
I dropped by daycare.
有人想见你
Somebody wanted to see you.
看那是谁呀?    你好  小子
Who's that? Hey, little man.
她的情况怎么样?      科特尔医生说她会没事
How is she doing? Doc Cottle says she'll be okay,
不过还要过段时间才能完全康复
but it's gonna be a while before she's 100 percent.
能行?
Yeah?
恩  没事     我知道  过来
Yeah, I'm fine. I know. Come here.
让我抱一下
I've got you.
想见妈妈了?
You want to go see Mommy? Want to go see Mommy?
走去见妈妈 来吧
Hey. Yeah. Let's go see Mommy. Come on.
她在这里
She's over here. Yeah.
阿莉
Cal.
亲爱的 看谁来了
Sweetie? Look who's here.
看谁来了
Look who's here.
希里克丝
Seelix.
无论如何
I don't know how we will manage
我们都会找到一个平衡点
to find a balance, you and me.
我们来抚养尼奇
We will take care of Nick.
好吗?     我爱你
Okay? I love you.
看 这是妈妈的手
Look. That's Mommy's hand.
在这里
There.
嗨  嗨
Hey. Hey.
你好吗?
How are you?
很好
Good.
这是什么?  我进来时就在那里了
So, what's this? It was here when I got in.
你父亲给你的
It's from your father.
是不是在"滴答  滴答"响?  他给你留了一张纸条
Is it ticking? He left you a note.
《卡布里卡刑法》
Caprican Criminal Codes.
这些是我祖父的法律书籍
These were my grandfather's law books.
一定是你父亲把这些书一直存放了起来
Your dad must have had these in storage all this time.
为什么他现在要给你?
Why is he giving them to you now?
献给我们都有时间的那一天
"For that day when we all have the time. "
很高兴你能顺便来这里 我有些东西要给你
ROSLIN: I'm glad you stopped by. I have something for you.
这是在新卡布里卡时  一个殖民者送给我的
This was given to me by one of the colonists down on New Caprica.
如果不是托莉在一堆旧衣服里发现了它 我就把这事给忘了
And I forgot about it and Tory found it in a pile of old clothes.
《午夜血光》
Blood Runs At Midnight.
别被书名骗到了 是一个很不错的神秘故事
Don't let the title fool you. It's a pretty good mystery.
我觉得你会喜欢
I think you'll like it.
不是借给你 而是送给你
And it's not a loan. It's a gift.
你还会时常想起在新卡布里卡上的那段时光吗?
Do you ever think about the times much on New Caprica?
我愿意去想好日子 是的  还会想起
I try to think about the good times. Yes, I do.
有一次  让我记忆犹新
One in particular stands out in my mind.
你那天穿着你那件鲜红色的裙子
You were wearing a really bright red dress.
还说你想造一座小屋
Said you wanted to build a cabin.
当时是波塔尔的奠基仪式
It was Baltar's groundbreaking ceremony.
那天晚上  我有点没头没脑的
I got a little silly that night.
你是否想过如果赛昂人没回来  又会发生什么事?
Do you ever wonder what would have happened if the Cylons hadn't come back?
考虑到波塔尔和当地的地形  我们也无法离开那里
Well, I think, given Baltar and the terrain, we couldn't have made a go of it.
你呢?  会留在卡拉狄加上?
What about you? Do you think you would have stayed on Galactica,
还是会定居在新卡布里卡?
or do you think you would have settled?
扯得太远了吧?
It's pretty hypothetical, isn't it?
是远了 可为时不远了
It is, until it isn't.
瞧我刚才说的是什么话
Did I just say that?
能看到你这样笑 也算值得了
It was worth just seeing you laugh like that.
战斗得太久 有时却忘了我们在为什么而战
We've been at war for so long, sometimes we forget what we're fighting for.
静心地抚养子女
To raise our kids in peace.
执子之手与子偕老 又可以享受正常的生活
Enjoy one another's company. Live life as people again.
比如像在新卡布里卡上的那个晚上
Like that night on New Caprica.
才是我们所真正向往的  对吧?
That's really what we are talking about here now, isn't it?
那时候 还有其他一些时候都算是
That, and other times.
那如果赛昂人没有回来的话?
So, if the Cylons hadn't come back...
但他们还是回来了
But they did.
我们有一定责任
We have certain responsibilities.
是的  长官  另外…
Yes, we do, sir, and...
我几天以后还会来
I will be back in a few days.
如果你愿意 我们可以再好好聊聊那天晚上的事
And if you'd like, we can talk more about that night.
比尔?
Bill?
答案是肯定的
The answer is yes.
我肯定会造那座小屋
I absolutely would have built the cabin.
去吧
CAROLANNE: Go ahead.
像每次结婚周年纪念日之后 你把它放起来一样
Put it away, like you have after every anniversary.
答应我 你不会再把它翻出来
Promise me you won't take it out again.
恨你或许更容易一些
ADAMA: Be easier to hate you.
可那就是在自欺欺人了 卡罗兰
But that would be a lie, Carolanne.
这一辈子 我们之间的谎言已经够多了
And there's been enough of that through our lives.
我们还是有值得纪念的事情的吧?
We had something, didn't we?
恩 是有
Yeah. We had something.
明年再见
See you next year.